<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<description trip="harvey" caption="Mt. Harvey">
 
<abstract>

<difficulty>
   <rating>D5</rating>
   <text>Steep ascent that gains close to 1400 vertical in just over 6km. Final summit block is an easy class 2 scramble in dry conditions</text>
</difficulty>

<trail>
    <rating>T3</rating>
    <text>Logging road followed by steep forest trail with cairns and flags. Trail fades in alpine but way is obvious</text>
</trail>

<snow-factor>
   <rating>S4</rating>
   <text>Frequently done as snowshoe trip. Steep and exposed summit block. Check avalanche conditions</text>
</snow-factor>

<scenery>
Exceptional Howe Sound panorama. Surprise Lions viewpoint at start of Harvey Ridge is among the best in Lower Mainland
</scenery>

<time>
   <value>7-8 hr</value>
   <text>3.5 - 4 hrs one way, with faster descent. Allow at least 1 hour for breaks and scenery on upper ridge</text>
</time>

<elevation start="220 m" max="1640 m" total="~1400 m"/>
<distance>13km</distance>

<gear>
Hiking Poles are essential. In late spring hard snow in steep parts might require traction (icers or crampons). In winter conditions ice-axe is essential for final part of the ridge before the summit
</gear>

<water>
Alberta creek running parallel (south) to Harvey trail. Access is difficult past split of Binkert trail. Carry 3L minimum
</water>

<dog>
<value>Yes</value>
<text>No on-leash restrictions. Final part of the ridge might prove challenging</text>
</dog>

</abstract>

<summary>
Of all trails radiating from Lions Bay, Mt. Harvey might be the most rewarding. It is less busy than Binkert (Lions) Trail and offers longest time above treeline. Steep slog through forest is still unavoidable, but final hour is superb ridgewalk with some of best possible views of Howe Sound. Parties ascend Harvey in winter conditions; but steepness of final slope leading to summit might require an ice-axe and elevates the trip to mountaineering level. In most years by 2nd half of May the snow has melted enough to provide just an easy rock scramble.
From standard parking at Lions Bay follow logging road keeping right at marked Brunswick/Lions junction in about 40 minutes.  Harvey trail branches off on the left side just before crossing of Alberta creek ~15 min from there.  Ascend steep forested slopes passing Howe Sound viewpoint around 1000m elevation (great spot for the break).  At start of south ridge turn left and follow flags through sub-alpine and open ridge to the summit
</summary>

<photo-corner>
   Mid-morning light is preferable for panoramic shots of Howe Sound from Harvey Ridge. For
   surprise view of the Lions from the start of the Ridge optimal conditions are in the afternoon when sun is already in the west.
   Sunset views from the ridge are among the best along Sea-to-Sky, but this requires either bivouac or descent in the dark
   under headlamp. In winter snow backdrop against blue ocean can be quite amazing
</photo-corner>
<going-further>
   It is possible to drop down Harvey east ridge and intersect Howe Sound Crest Trail near Harvey Pass. This would allow for loop
   return via Magnesia Meadows and Brunswick Trail. Due to ridge steepness it can not be recommended. It is much better to do
   this loop in opposite direction.
</going-further>

</description>